Hello, welcome everyone. It is active
inference guest stream 125.1 on December
17th, 2025.
And we are with a group of researchers
who will each present in sequence
presenting on from Charles Darwin's root
brain to Nicola Tesla's 6G worldbrain
and XAI native 6G networks. So Martin,
Nika Osman, thank you all for joining
and looking forward to your presentation
to you Martin. Thank you.
>> Thank you Daniel. So thanks for having
us. So this is uh a co-presentation of
three uh speakers. I will go first
followed by Nika and Osman.
Uh just let me Okay. So I will draw the
big picture. So the overarching goal is
to realize an AGI standing for
artificial general intelligence native
6G world brain.
uh of course using active inference.
Nika will elaborate on the super
superiority of active inference compared
to generative AI and finally Osman will
uh show some ideas how to exploit active
inference for realizing explainable AI.
So the vision of a world brain goes back
to Tesla Nicola Tesla who made this
famous prophecy when wireless is fully
applied the earth will be converted into
a huge brain. This has been standing
there for decades. The point is that
with emerging 6G and beyond technologies
we are now close to realizing his
prophecy.
uh enabling technologies such as joint
sensing and communication give rise to
distributed sensing environment which
together um create this perception arcs
this sensing arc uh similar to uh active
inference there will be also a loop back
an action arc and there is a lot of
research currently going on I just uh
mentioned two buzzwords it's about AI
embodiment and agentic AI I. So there
needs to be research to be done. But
once this is done, you can see that this
AI native telecom brain creates a
gigantic action perception loop similar
to active inference.
This hi native telecom brain has been
proposed in this in this sorry about
this background noise. Uh in this paper
you can find it on iTle Explorer. Uh
these are leading 6G scientists. The
interesting part is in this paper the
term active inference is not mentioned
once. Likewise uh Carl Fristen is not
mentioned once. These are stellar
researchers but completely unaware of
active inference. Of course we follow a
different approach. We apply active
inference and couple it with a number of
other strategies such as MIT's human AI
strategy which in a nutshell simply ask
this question. So what would happen if
we replace AI neurons with people? Keep
in mind we want to build a gigantic
world brain and it's not only humans but
also so-called hyper inelligent
cybernetic organ or organisms will which
will emerge from existing AI systems in
the coming age of hyper intelligence.
The good news is that these cybernetic
organisms will not compete with us
humans but live in a mutually beneficial
symbiosis with us human beings and
because they are so superior they will
consider us humans as we now regard
plants. This sounds like bad news, but
actually it's an invitation for us to
explore this so-called evolutionary
continuum of human and this is the
official term from ecologist more than
human intelligence. An example is the
so-called wood web. So this term
woodwide web made some waves back in the
90s when it was published in nature. A
more technical term is microisal
networks. This is goes back to two
two Greek terms
uh risel that means roots and mico that
means fungi. So these are two different
species with which live in in symbiosis.
Symbiosis comes in a number of different
flavors. It can be negative such as
parasitism but microisal networks
realize a mutually beneficial mutilism
type of symbiosis.
So this symbiotic flora fungi mutilism
forms a new research field in biology.
It's highlighted down here. So it's all
about decentralized exchange of
information resources and exchanging
reciprocal rewards to create a community
and res resilience underground of all
forests.
And you have these roots underground and
of course roots of different trees are
separated. But there's a third layer,
these so-called fungi that
um connect these uh roots of different
trees of different species in order to
create um an ecosystem. This has been
observed
years ago by Charles Darwin and Charles
Darwin coined the term root.
So this is a very packed figure. I
mention it only some some highlights. So
remember our goal is to build a world
brain. However, given that active
inference is a biomimatic framework, we
take inspiration from uh nature, more
specifically root brain. So we start
with root brain, try to understand it
and then replicate it in the virtual
worlds of the emerging metaverse. To do
so, we have to develop lifelike
cybernetic organisms which require the
convergence of digital evolution and
biology. Giving rise to these
aforementioned lifelike cybernetic
organisms. This is a generic term. An
example of lielike cybernetic organisms
are these cyber fungi. And their role is
to symbiomic these fungal networks
properties such as transfer of resources
from areas of abundance to scarcity from
larger plants to smaller plants. So you
see it's just the opposite of
competition. It's really collaboration
and mutual support. And this is because
of entropy. Entropy is the nature's
hidden force driving life to
equilibrium. In our work, we also
include a certain twist which makes
things more interesting. As you might
know from thermodynamics, equ uh entropy
must stay the same or increase. But we
use generative AI to change the laws of
physics by also reducing ent uh entropy.
This is done by using uh generative AI.
More specifically, we use generative AI
to dynamically couple two types of life
cycles. So on one hand, we have plant
life cycles such as trees. On the other
side, we have mushroom life cycles. So
mushrooms are the fruing body of those
underground fungi. So simply put, we we
create cyber fungi which mimic fungi in
order to hallucinate a certain type of
um network structure. The technical term
is scale-free networks with small world
properties in order to connect different
plants and their life cycles. Then these
fungi might embody themselves into
mushrooms and each mushroom has a
separate life cycle. So you see here a
plant produces spores. Uh it's pollen,
excuse me, and mushrooms produce borus.
The interesting part is now these are
biological terms. What does it mean in
human terminology? So pollen might be
translated into social norms like
cross-pollination.
So we spread one pollen from one plant
to another plant. This is like in human
societies. We spread a social norm from
person A to person B. And spores an
human equivalent of biological spores
might be teological tokens such as
purpose-driven tokens widely used in
blockchain networks. So generative AI
there are different types of generative
API. We opted for OpenAI's improved
DDPM. This is open source. DTPM stands
for dnoising diffusion probabilistic
models and it comes in two um
complimentary processes. So we have a
forward process called diffusion. This
forward process increases entropy. So it
creates disorder and of course this
backward processes reverses the u
process by reducing uh entropy. So
creating order out of disorder. This is
illustrated for a specific use case of
DTPM image generation. So this is the
backward process. We start with this
order with chaos technically speaking
white noise and then we let the dnoising
process unfold itself and like like
magically out of thin air it
hallucinates a realistic uh image which
was not in the training data set. So
this is really like like magic.
The trick and the challenge was to adapt
DDPM from an image generation context to
our root brain context. So simply put,
you have to understand how these fungi
work, identify the processes and map
these biological processes to DTPM's
forward and backward process. So
specifically the forward diffusion
process of DTPM was used to biomimic the
so-called branching process and
exploratory tendency of fungi.
Conversely, the backward denoising
process of DTPM was used to biomimic
another set of processes carried out by
the root brain namely fusing and homing
process.
This was all generative AI so far and of
course we can do the same using active
inference. This is the graphical model
of our active inference uh uh generative
model. So you have a number of
parameters those working in active
inference recognize them. G is the uh
expected free energy uh B is the
transition matrix and this is the
graphical model behind every box. Of
course you have a number of equations
and as you know at least those working
on active inference a generative model
is typically uh developed using this pom
dp partially observable markup decision
process. This is what we did and then we
were interested in comparing generative
AI to active inference. For this we had
to define a use case. Our use case was a
bunch of people, 64 people, humans, and
one person starts performing a new
behavior and we were interested how long
it takes that until the new behavior is
propagating through the entire
population. So, we have two metrics. I
will break it down on the following
slides because this figure is a little
bit too packed. Important is how to read
the x-axis. You have to read it from
left to right. This is the forward
process of DTPM. And then vice versa
from right to left. This is the
secondary backward process of DTPM. Now
I break it down. So we were interested
in the first metric. It's just the
number of time units it takes till a new
behavior is propagated through the
entire population. And the black are the
blue solid lines. This is the forward
process. So we start with a number of uh
curves. This is dependent on a small
parameter r. This is simply the
spreading probability of the new
behavior. So the probability that the
new behavior jumps from person over to
person B. And as you can see as the
forward process is unfolding the number
of required timers is dropping rapidly
and then hits a plateau. It stays flat
and then from red to left we enter the
backward process. This is the dash red
line and it's interesting what's
happening at the end. You can see the
red curve stays flat. It does not go
back up as the initial curves. And this
is very interesting because it it tells
us that with a uh DTPM we achieve
minimum number of time uh units it takes
to propagate a certain behavior through
population. And the second important
observation is it's completely
independent of the spreading
probability. So it doesn't matter
whether you are more a less willing to
adapt a new behavior. generative AI is
so powerful to keep the minimum uh at
two time limits. Then a second metric
was kind of how to incentivize people.
You know, if you want you have a group
of 64 people, you ask them please adapt
this and that behavior. Of course, this
behavior should be desirable. But you
can also um encourage incentivize
people. This is done by token. So
whenever a couple of person people uh
decide to adapt a new behavior, each
person is rewarded with one token.
Again, I keep it short here due to time
limit. Uh the uh green curve is the
forward process. These dash purple uh
curves are the backward process. This
bunch of curves uh curves hover over
2,500
tokens roughly. Keep this number in mind
because we compared it to active
inference. So it's a typical figure.
It's like a cost function we have to
invest to to uh incentivize behavior.
The [snorts] cost function is around
2,500 tokens. Then we did the same use
case bunch of 64 people with active
inference. First metric the time it
takes to achieve full social contagion.
It's a little bit slower. Instead of two
time units, it's one, but it's
comparable. The main main difference is
in the cost function. So instead of 200
2,500,
we have only 250 tokens to spend. So
active inference really outperforms
generative AI by one order of magnitude
by a factor of 10.
Why is it? because active inference as
opposed to generative AI is able of
lifelong learning. This is illustrated
here. On the y-axis we have the belief
update magnitude and on the xaxis the uh
active inference process unfolding. So
let's start with dtpm the generated.
This is the dashed yellowish curve. You
see there's one learning event but then
at the process is unfolding no more
further learning is taking place very
different from generative AI active
inference there's a huge learning peak
at the beginning and then there are is
continuous learning throughout the
process so one question we ask ourselves
is whether there's a way to further
enrich this lifelong learning process of
active inference and this brought us to
a new field. It's AI and psychedelic
medicine. Believe it or not, this is a
nent intersecting area of generative AI
and psychedelics. Psychedelics is now
part of mainstream medicine to cope with
uh mental health issues such as
depression and anxiety. [snorts] And the
trick is of course we want to uh make AI
not only a biomimeatics but also
psychedelic mimatics meaning all the
benefits of psychedelics are also
realized in AI. Of course the question
is how to do this. So the main challenge
is how to integrate the cognitive
mechanisms activated by psychedelics
into our AI design.
Doing this also has the nice benefit of
addressing one of the shortcomings of
active inference. As you might know,
active inference is all about surprise
minimization. This necessarily leads to
this well-known problem of dark room
problem. So if an active inference agent
continuously performs active inference
meaning surprising uh minimizing
surprise the agent will sooner or later
end up in a dark room because nothing is
happening there. No surprise is
happening there. Of course this is
counter to what we expect from life. But
instead of seeing it as a problem, we
should see it as an invitation to close
our eyes and turn our attention from the
external action perception loop inward.
Okay? And neuroscientists use this term
brain dark energy. So whenever we close
our eyes, our brain is not doing less,
just the opposite. some parts of the
brain really lit up and consume up to 20
times uh more energy when at rest and
this is uh the path forward. So we have
to extend expand active inference by a
secondary complimentary
uh theory. It's known as entropic brain
theory. Of course KL Frisen already
worked on this. So psychedelics have two
benefits. It not only widens the free
energy landscape but it also flattens
the minima so it's easier to escape a
local minima order to explore the
widened uh free energy landscape. So I'm
almost done and then I hand it over to
NA. So in our work and we can report
some results on this. Our aim first aim
was to advance active inference from a
biological aging context to a
psychoactive agent. Uh luckily nature
produces psychoactive agents which come
in three flavors. Stimulants such as
caffeine, seditive if you undergo a
surgery you use sedatives such as opium
and of course the third one hallogens
such as psilocybin. And the interesting
part is only this the third one produces
this um characteristic this feature we
are trying to harness mental plasticity.
So only hloenogenic
agents are capable of inducing the state
of mental plasticity and this is what we
want to mimic in our AI design. And to
do so we had to go back to the
generative model of active inference.
Recall typically it uses the concept of
pom dp. So it comes with a standard set
of variables and matrices. None of them
is suitable to accommodate psychedelics.
So you have to explore the so-called pom
dp pom dp extension and then you find
something which captures the prior
belief of agents D. And our goal is to
induce mental plasticity. And to do so,
we have to weaken uh the prior belief D
of uh active inference agent. And this
is done by decreasing a certain
parameter known as precision parameter
omega norm. And this is my final slide.
So this is something just for
illustration how EBT really kicks in. On
the y-axis you have the entropy of prior
belief. Okay. And on the x-axis again
the active inference process unfolding.
We compare two different active
inference agents. The red one is a
conventional active inference without
any EBT enhancement and it does what
it's supposed to do throughout the
process. The agent tries to minimize uh
surprise meaning minimizing entropy. And
this is for survival. It's good purpose
for learning. It's not the best strategy
because minimizing surprise of course
avoids surprise and epistemic
opportunities.
The second agent was put under
psychedelic for a temporary window
between time step 500 and time step uh
1,000. And then you can see the entropy
of the second second um uh agents belief
really shoots up and then it stays flat.
This being flat also nicely um reflects
this so-called psychedelic afterglow
effect of psychedelics.
This is good news because it shows that
EBT is really able to increase entropy
and increasing entropy in our terms
means you know it enables divergent
thinking and this is instrumental in in
uh increasing creativity of our AI
agents and 6G world brain. This is all
from my side. Now I hand it over to Na.
Thank you.
Okay, I will now share my slides.
Okay.
So, hello everyone. My name is Nika. I
will now go into the implementation
details of both generative AI and active
inference agents. Uh compare their
difference and compare the performance
through results and then explain how we
actually modified it with sleep, rest
and psychedelics to solve the dark room
problem.
Okay. Uh here we compare generative AI
versus active inference. With generative
AI we have disembodied passive AI but
with active inference we have embodied
active AI. Embodied means it has an
actual action perception look that acts
in the board. With generative AI we have
no belief updating after initial
training. But with active inference we
have continuous bian belief updating.
uh here outputs are created with
generative AI without acting in the
environment. But with active inference,
actions are selected by uh inferring
posterior over policies. With generative
AI, we have pattern matching perception.
It means that generative AI does not
truly understand it inputs. It just um
detects statistical patterns in the data
and just matches the statistical
patterns.
But with active inference we have
perception as inferences of latent
causes. It means that active inference
actually understanded um hidden causes
behind everything that happens in the
world.
Here we get inspired by the microisal
networks. So microisal networks has
three features that we get inspired by
branching fusing and intreating. With
branching we have exploration. So fungal
filaments extend into the soil which
mimic outward growth as exploration and
increasing entropy and fusing is kind of
an exploitation. So connection fused to
redistribute nutrients and restore order
and resource consolidation
and with entreating or embodiment fruing
bodies emerge emerge to act in the
world. So it bridges dialogical and
biological um digital and biological
agency.
Here we created 1.3 million small word
scale-free graph structures using
network X in Python. So using network X
we created these graphs. Small word
means the network has tightly connected
local groups and scaffree means that the
network uh has a few highly connected
hops and many smaller nodes. So we here
we encode the symmetric binary tensors
as zero and one. So we have 64 humans
that u these humans are representing and
as nodes and the social links are
representing as edges. So here when we
have an edge we put one when we don't
have an edge we put zero and we feed
this uh data set into um the DDPM so we
get adjacency tensors at outputs but in
output we also necessarily don't have
the binary output so we have a two-stage
binarization threshold which is 0.5 if
it's above this threshold we put one it
means humans are connected if it's under
this threshold we put zero
And here cyber fungi acts as an adaptive
generative AI agent and we do dynamic
edge wiring with teological tokens. So
here we try to do a social contagion
norm. So the sparing probability is
between zero and one.
So this is a general overview of the
pomdb based graphical model of active
inference. I will now break down the
slides into detail.
So the agent model components are state
factors, control factors and observation
modalities. So here state factors are
SORM, SMB, SNEV and STOK. SNORM is
better agent adopted the social norm and
SMB is for meta beliefs. So is what I
think my neighbor believes and SNET is
the network structure which means
presence or absence of edges and STOK is
whether cyber fungi issued aological
token. For control factors we have cyber
fungi agency and human agency. With
cyber fun agency we have unit and uto
is reviring adding or pruning edges to
accelerate contagion and you talk is
token assignment to reward norm adopters
with human agency. So humans attend to
norm and metabelief because humans
should decide whether to adopt or reject
a norm and they should decide whether to
select a neighbor to sample new evidence
from and also observation modalities are
the same. We have four categories and
humans attend to norm and OM and cyber
fungi attend to on net and auto.
Here are the generative model
parameters. So we have a likelihood
tensor which map hidden states to
observation probabilities. We have a
transition matrix with show temporal
evolution of beliefs and priors D and E.
So D is initial beliefs over hidden
states and E is initial beliefs over
actions
and there is a C which is the outcome
preference vector u which is the goal
vector that we have.
Uh this slide summarizes the free energy
principle as a unified framework. So pre
free energy principle measures the
difference between what the agent
believes and what's true and each agent
minimizes f to reduce surprise and
select optimal action and expected free
energy is about the future. So we try to
anticipate the value of future outcomes
under the policy P with this formula.
A key challenge with active inference is
that we have computational tractability
because we have 64 humans. The size of
transition or likelihood matrices is 2 ^
64 * 2 ^ 64. How we solve this
challenge? So we divide
these 64 into each sub factors. So
the these sub factors has either base +
one or base.
So then only we need 2 ^ b i * 2 ^ of b
i likelihood or transition matrices.
Uh this slide compares ddpm with active
inference. So
with r equals to one it means spreading
probability equals to one. We see that
af time is 1. and DDPM time is 2.5 for
social contagion of all nodes. So not
only active inference has less needs
less time to have the social contagion
of all nodes but we have 10 times more
token efficiency. So AF achieves order
of magnitude lower token cost than DDPM.
This slide looks at the small word
index. So the small word index uh this
is the formula and it shows the ratio
of clustering and path length relative
to a random network. A rule of thumb
says if the sigma or a small word
network is bigger than one we have a
small word regime. Here if you look the
DDPM agents small word
um a small word index is much more
higher than the AF agent. So DDPM
preserves a small word structure better
than AIF. Here's why. Because DDPM
shortens the path length and also
increases the clustering coefficient.
Here is the belief dynamics. So delta KL
is obtained with this formula and it
measures how much an agent updates its
belief from one step to the next. So
it's kind of a kale divergence of QS and
QS minus one. Here AIF has multiple
recurring spikes uh spikes during um
which are [clears throat] decreasing
over time which shows genuine learning
and DDPM only has a single early uh peak
which drops to zero which shows the
minimal learning here.
So, professor Meyer completely explained
why uh what is dark room problem. Now,
I'm going to explain what is our
resolution. So,
the resolution is that it's not just the
brain minimizing uh the surprise. It's
the agent environment.
So, it means that uh the resolution is
that uh in stimulating environments, the
best way to reduce long-term uncertainty
is actually to explore. This is called
the enlightened room view.
And here we have the neural evidence
which is the break brain's dark energy.
So brain uses 60 to 80% energy at rest
and the default mode network or the DMN
is active in rest for simulation, recall
and pres uh preparation and intrinsic
brain activity is
20 times more than external stimulus
response. So it highlights exploration
uh exploration as a baseline. So we try
to disengage from action perception loop
through sleep, rest and psychedelics to
allow exploration within internal space.
Here is the first modification we do
through sleep cycle which is the Bayia
model reduction. Our core concept is
that Beijian model reduction prunes
redundant connections similar to the
sleep cycle and in absence of new data
complexity minimization becomes our
first goal. Here we calculate delta f uh
which is the free energy difference
between two models. Here you can see a
is the posterior cont concentration
parameter from observed data and a till
is the prior parameters of the full
model. A prime is the edge removal
candidate for model reduction and B
quantifies the model evidence. So we
calculate delta F from here and if it is
less than zero it is in favor of the
reduced model.
There are two stage for sleep routine.
Stage one is resetting priors for each
hidden state factors. So we override
prior DF to posterior QF and this
naturally removes the kale divergence
term between QF and DF. The second stage
is pruning edges. So for each edge uv we
construct the reduced model and compute
the delta f. If this is less than -3, it
means that we prune the edge.
This was the original BMR. So we have we
propose an enhanced BMR cycle which has
repeating cycles of wake, wake and
sleep. This is a loop which shows
continuous adaptation. In during each
wake we add three edges and during each
sleep we remove the weakest 20% of
posterior QET edges.
Here are the results of the Beijian
model reduction and confidence dynamics.
So here you can see that we have the
single cycle BMR that f reduces from 10
to 9.75 which delta if is 0.25 nets.
Here is the multicycle with guided
pruning. So it is our proposed BMR. You
can see that it goes from 10.5 to 9.25
here. So it reduces by 1.25. So it has a
five times larger reduction in free
energy. The next metric is confidence
dynamics. So confidence uh is showing
for example high confidence is clear
agent rule. Confidence is obtained from
negative entropy [clears throat] of QET.
So and lower confidence is showing a
structural uncertainty or uniform Q.
Here you can see that the multicycle
agent has higher confidence than the
wake only agent.
The second modification we do is through
rest. So during rest, the brain exhibits
a spontaneous activity across resting
state networks and RSM maximize uh
special templar entropy reflecting the
brain's generative model for future
adaptability
and accuracy is deemphasized here. So we
want to map rest fases to PMDP based AF
framework. We have five stages. First we
disengage from external inputs. Then we
suppress accuracy and try to do maximum
entropy policy sampling. So we try to
build the fictive trajectories and
sample from categorical priors and
categorical transition matrices. And
using these frictive trajectories we try
to update the dural parameters A and B.
Here are the results. We builded spatial
a special spatial entropy temporal
entropy and a spatial temporal entropy.
Here a spatial entropy measures the
diversity of network clustering. So here
you can see that weight plus stress
agent has more spatial entropy. It means
that it has more distributed and
flexible connectivity. With temporal
entropy we uh we capture irregularity of
norm. And here you see that there is uh
a little or no difference between them
which higher um temporal entropy
indicates more asynchronous norm
switching between agents and spatial
temporal entropy capture both spatial
and temporal entropy features. So you
can see it's with wake plus rest agent
we have a little more special temporal
entropy and because we suppressed
accuracy in the wake plus rest agent you
see that accuracy here is less than the
accuracy in wake only accuracy shows the
negative expected surprise and it's the
predictive alignment between beliefs and
observations.
The third modification we do is brain
theory unification under psychedelics.
So, Professor Fson's work merges free
energy principle with entropic brain
theory which links computational
neurobiological and experimental insight
into a single explanatory model. Here we
uh try to do precision relaxation. So
using psychedelics we relax the
precision of highle priors. This fosters
openness and cognitive flexibility. Then
we uh then this increases entropy. So
psychedelics temporarily increase brain
entropy which allows escape from uh
repetitive patterns of thoughts and
promoting novel neural trajectory. And
then we have expanded accessibility. So
this expand the brain's accessible
state. uh so it allows the emergence of
uh new cognitive configurations.
Here we uh deactivate the default mode
network. The default mode network or DMN
is the part of the brain responsible for
self-referential thinking and rigid
patterns of thought. And then we have
the psychedelic afterlow which is the
period uh after psychedelic effect wears
off. So the brain settles into a state
that is stable but more flexible than
before.
Here are the results of cognitive
dynamics under psychedelics which shows
the prior entropy. Here you have uh the
prior entropy results. The prior entropy
measures the uncertainty of priors. Here
you can see that with psychedelics and
through psychedelic window we are we
have more prior entropy which means we
have flexible priors and it also stays
the same after the psychedelic window
which means uh we have the psychedelic
after glow effect.
Next we try to second we try to um show
the posterior synchrony. uh so we
measure posterior synchrony or belief
coherence which captures how aligned
agent beliefs are across the networks.
So here high synchrony means that we
have coherent beliefs. So with wake only
agent we have coherent beliefs but with
wake plus uh with um psychedelic agent
we don't have coherent beliefs. So it's
it's trying to enhance the exploration
instead of coherent beliefs. Our final
use case is the comparison of AF
enhancements. So we compare all the
prior entropies of all agents with
sleep, rest, psychedelics. You can see
that sleep has most prior entropy and
wake has the least prior entropy.
Okay, here Osmo will take over and
explain about active inference and
explain explainable AI. Thank you. Thank
you, Nico. Let me share my uh slid set.
Oops. So,
you can see I guess right
now. Yeah. Okay. So, uh first of all,
welcome everyone. I'm Mosmanai on the
behalf of Technical University of Berlin
and Fran Homefare HHI Institute. But uh
we were collaborating with INR
especially of course professor Meyer
last one year over and I was visiting um
him this uh summer this summer uh in the
Canada. So that's I will try to do um
basically come up with the um how we can
combine active inference in the in the
in the sense of u next generation
wireless networks. Specifically, I will
uh after this theoretical size of the
research, I will come up with the more
application domain for the next
generation wireless as I said 6GN 6G
beyond uh architecture and my like my
research focus was explainable AI and AI
I'm an AI scientist for wireless. So I
will try to combine these two
methodology in a way that with our
recent research. So let's start with the
uh our uh very foundational information
age um um um terms and the paradigms
which is the uh maybe in in your
community it's not maybe very familiar
but like cloud Shannon was the like
define the nowadays that we are knowing
what is the communication network so how
the one two asset can communicate in a
way that information source to
destination source how the message goes
basically the How today whatever you
know about the wireless or telephone
technology is comes comes up with this
diagram the basically the we call it
this information age that was the end of
40s early 50s this this design was
happen uh but um while he was uh
designing information age he was also of
course interested on the learning
machines thinking machines as like Ellen
Turing but of while he was doing this
specifically as our today's um talks the
the title Darwin's root brain theory he
was also aware that Darin was also um
coming up for the like this uh bio
biology inspired machine so cloud
Shannon was also was the aware of it
while designing this wireless um
communication backbone he was also
working on the learning learnable or
like machine machine technologies or
like logical machines so this isant
important why because like last Ner IPS
conference I was talking with the Mikail
Wand Shar from University Cambridge. So
the idea behind this wireless community
and the AI community needs to work back
to back to design efficiently of this
the the upcoming uh technologies because
nowadays 62% of the worldwide internet
is used by mobile networks while this AI
interaction happening. So that's very
important actually the statistic when we
thinking about it. Okay. After the very
theoretical introduction then when we
check about like we call it nowadays
what is happening on the communication
is we call this this this um period is
um post Shannon era. Post channel era
basically what is as you can previously
the first slide you can remember that
what we are like trying to send the
throw bits towards uh transmitter to
receiver. uh it's classical like channel
channel is our the you know the uh the
place that where we send the over the
our uh message so but you can see that
post channel row is a bit different
because now we are started to train our
AI models especially the artificial
general intelligence models like
foundation models to make more efficient
coding um network coding on the like
physical layer or if we go I will of
course come up with new slides and
regarding our uh research it's even for
the upper layers like the semantic
knowledge. So rather than to sending
only row bits like you know the data or
it can be voice it can be whatever the
image now we can basically tell the
network that what is our intent what we
want to send it to receiver so that's to
nowadays we call it post channel and
error that's why the AI is heavily
integrated on the 5G
then we are trying to make basically the
AI native 6G so that was the reason and
you can see from here as I said AI
already on the 5G is deployed so many uh
different countries different factory
settings or self-driving cars anywhere
because when we thinking about today's
like Vimo in the like San Francisco
these cars needs to communicate with the
edge servers over the wireless so they
and when we thinking about use cases url
means ultra reliable low latency
communication or the EMBB like the video
recording or video screening should be
very like prioritized on the network
this can prioritization or the resource
allocation can done with the
conventional AI techniques. But this is
not enough because we are going further
more sub 3 GHz activated bands which
means more data rate and more capacity
of the network. Then we can basically go
more uh it's it's called advanced ultra
reliable low latency communication. So
this is coming towards near realtime
interactions with the network towards
the uh components of the real real life.
So how it looks like I mean when we
thinking about we're starting early age
some of some of us maybe catch 3G some
of us maybe 2G
we realize it how it's changed basically
you can see that what we are
transferring was text to voice now we
are talking about space communications
tactile internet like the today's like
like optimus robot hand um and
interactions with the real time um uh
life in the like or act of life and as
as well as automated cars like um um
like drones or digital tins they are the
they are the now the the data sources or
like the data um applications that we
are using towards 6G. So that's very
important and as you can see we are like
50 kilobit per second to one terabit uh
terabyte per second communication we are
talking and included quantum
communication we call it like quantum
aware communications in the in our
domain. So this is a this is a big
change basically it's not like from 2D
to 3G. So we are basically designing the
AI native uh AI native 6G. every layer
of the protocol stack is communicating
with different sort of um AI algorithms
or let's call it learning learning um
learning algorithms because some of them
can be conventional uh you know machine
learning techniques because you don't
need the much more reasoning capacity or
like cognitive inspired agents there but
most of the time uh every layer it's
this now we are designing to deploy 2030
to this technology with AI native so
that's very it brings very important
responsibility. That's why one of the
very important pillars of this um AI
native 6G design is secure and
trustworthiness. So why this is very
important? You can see this the ITU is
international telecommunication union
and 3GPP is the nowadays like any of
generation of the technology like 2G,
3G, 4G, 5G is uh defined specification
of the 3GPP which is included different
companies, different institutes. they
are like the biggest institutes in the
world that they define the mobile or
wireless networks uh specifications. So
while they are doing this when they when
you check their recent reports ITU R IMT
uh like the 2030 report as well as the
3GPP is the last specification one of
the biggest important uh pillars are
trustworthiness trustworthiness means
since we are designing AI native 6G we
should aware that the there should there
shouldn't be like a problem regarding
trustworthiness expl or interoperable
um decision points in the network uh
while the network operating because
there are so many um communication
environments like energy grid networks
like you can think about you know this
the electricity problems happen in
Portuguese or like this the uh nuclear
centrals or like you can think about
tele operations smart hospitals or very
low latency applications on the smart
factories is like a very high production
lines so then this means that while okay
we are doing this AI native design we
should be aware that this AI
doesn't degradate degragate the network
performance. So that's why this
trustworthiness or explanability aspect
of design come to play. Now I want to
show that okay we we talk about coming
from the AI native design to explainable
aspects and I want to come up with our
uh in technical university of Berlin
what we did some explainable AI research
and then how we we can um get advantage
of the active imperence in our use
cases. One of the use case for instance
remote controlled robot you can use this
robot anywhere like it can be some
earthquake situation it can be some
exploration purposes anything else. So
while you are using that you can maybe
want to allocate your resource because
there should be used in this scenario
one one real um uh real uh robot remote
control robot but you can use so many of
them. So then you need to be aware of
your network uh usage or network uh
resource allocation problem. That's why
you can use some uh prediction models on
the top of your network. It's called
that's why AI native and while this
network communicating it can be oper uh
you can your AI algorithm can operate
some uh resource allocation problem for
your components of your uh design. But
again very important we are now talking
about earthquake. there could be some
lives or it we can talk about this robot
can be basically working on the smart
factory environment and making some
operations. So then we should be aware
again our prediction AI model or like
learning model or like deep learning
model or any reinforcement learning
agent should be transparent and not
blackbox. That's why the we designed in
our AI algorithm top of it some XI
design to make it transparently
available. Any other any other story
other story this was like a work with
the northeastern university from uh US
as well as India networks from Spain and
NSF funed and we I mean one of the very
biggest topic also in our communication
or like any other when you check the
companies digital events which means
very low latency applications of the
real world components to uh digital
replica of it. Why? Then we can
basically simulate so many different
scenarios
um of like that real life component.
What could be production lines? What
could be uh again like the smart medical
applications? what could be robotic
environments. Nowadays when we are
talking about this humanoids uh their
digital tables can be trained in a low
cost and more efficient domains or even
um I was at NIPS and there was a Tesla's
presentation they are basically training
their controller
for the like this uh so-called digital t
simulator. So that type of applications
are very important. So you don't need to
deploy the whole bench of network or
technology stack. So that's why we made
it in our um collaboration. We got the
one of the collesium um uh digital tin
to create a 6G network or 5G network in
this sense here and then we basically
created some different sparse datas with
the generative AI. So the the main idea
now we are working on that to make okay
we are creating some synthetic data for
the like digital t layer but is it
really performance okay in a in a in a
sense of AI KPIs it's it seems good but
we should check that is the model is uh
um operating in a good way that's why
the XI was coming to play and and one
other uh story was again in the
molecular communication domain we in our
projects called internet of bioano
things. So this is also very important
for the active inference people as well
as the nikas and the professor meers
side of the theory because now it's
basically this AI models work for the
biology um biology um environments. So
we were basically what we did is we
again when you think about the
communication network it was immune cell
was the um uh transmitter and tumor cell
was the receiver because when the tumor
cell comes towards the immune cell
immune cell started to release some sort
of um um biochemical um components. So
that's why we try to use some AI
algorithms like especially very simple
uh uh feed neural network to understand
that which there was a two feature one
is the like the estim the distance and
other one was the released amount of
molecules so while we using this AI we
want to make it which component is much
more efficient in our this nanocale
design because it's very important then
we have a knowledge about okay this
feature is more informative in the sense
of cancer research. So that's why we use
explanability in the sense of this
research. Lately I said the in
communication there there should be
there are some research domains on the
uh physical layer but as well as the our
latest research with like big
collaborative work we try to basically
on the higher level of the network
component semantically we want to
transfer the knowledge. I don't want to
get that much detail but in this work we
try to basically get um reasoning
capacity and then the human expert can
communicate with basically the network
components in a way that with LLM way
like the GPT models foundation models so
that was the reason that's why we call
it reasoning model so whatever it
happens in the lower layer like let's
say physical layer parts of the network
it gets it's generates some graph neural
uh some graphs and we convert it to
knowledge graphs basically with the
human human interpretable statements
then human can interact with the like
network which is normally it's not the
case in our today's conventional
communication mobile network. So that
was the novelty of this work. So uh when
we thinking about this is like this is a
big change I'd say that starting from
Shannon to post Shannon this was the
from Huawei's report and they also like
in the glocom they presented efficiently
they want to change the full like
nowadays how we knowing the the
communication networks they want to
change it for the like full LLM GPT wise
network for instance they called their
user equipment which is our phones is uh
for them um uh AI phone or or like they
call it AI REN. So everything is work
with the LLM uh integrated agentic
vision. So which is a which is upcoming
reality. So when we think about like
it's again uh this this this movement
towards agentic design for so many
different applications as again
professor my nikab was focusing on the
uh in their talk like 3D networking
blockchain technologies or holographic
teleresence we should also like as we
said as a wireless designer or like the
6G scientists we should come up with
more
um re um cognitively capable agents. So
that's why the point of active inference
was coming to play with our discussions
with the professor meer and then we
discussed like how we can do it and then
my interest was more explanability and
he he was on the like the more design of
active inference for 6G. So we started
of course with the state-of-the-art. So
what is happening in our in our domain?
What's uh what is like usage of the uh
learning techniques? Most common
technique in everywhere again
reinforcement learning techniques for we
call it network slicing. So the network
compon network resources sliced between
the prioritization of the scenario in
the sense maybe um autonomous car very
low latency communication some maybe
smart hospital or maybe IoT sensors or
maybe some ARVR glasses. So for them
that's a efficient work for the like uh
nowadays they use it in the wireless
domain. So this is again traditional way
and then we designed in our like
well-known uh backbone of the um
uh active inference agent we call it
brain because this is the from the our
paper's name based in reasoning where
active inference for explainable mobile
networks. Why we did it? The idea is
again the same comes with the
trustworthiness. You can use a
reinforcement learning but you are not
sure agents behavior. It can be a a
degregated network performance but we
can use the posterior beliefs here to
represent the agents beliefs towards the
upcoming decision action point regarding
the states. That's why we come up with
this design. I don't I don't want to get
that much deep details because it's a
very long paper and under the review of
conference and the uh journal. So that's
why I want to give up like what was the
design in like a bit abstract way. So
what we did is uh more than theory
basically we applied uh active inference
uh design brain agent to directly um um
GPU accelerated radio access network
which in the sense of different users
three different users and then we try to
basically visualize the agents beliefs
with the help of this um posterior
belief design of the active inference
itself by nature. So this is inherently
there. So that's why we want to use it
in a way that how agent is seeing the
network um network um state. So as you
can see for instance in our three
different slice scenario in in EMBB
slice which is like this most like most
connectivity like you can think about
ARVR application here agents start with
like he say that like regarding the
first initial data prioritization in
initialization he the agent or he she or
it directly says that oh there's an high
demand which is actually when when you
think about it it's a it's it makes
sense because the there is a demand end
of the uh down link from the application
domain. So that was makes sense and this
was our checkpoints and in some some
sort of after the uh the user equipment
reached the network the agent itself it
says that okay now it's getting more
lower and this is like a as you can see
this is the like belief probability the
belief probability now the demand of the
demand state or like the need of this
resources for EMBB slice is lower and I
mean same for the like different I mean
different priority or different interest
or different demand state for ultra
reliable low latency but we were like
efficiently see that agents behavior in
a posterior belief state of course in
the paper uh there is much more extreme
and in restricted u agent uh behavior
and then it's it's it's a it's a long
paper so I will be happy to share uh
when the results came so and lately
again very fruitful result for us was
the like when we check about the mean
cumulative reward we because we want to
in our scenario. We want to see the
conventional reinforcement learning
techniques su success and compare with
this baselines and you can see that our
uh the brain agent basically much more
efficient in our non-stationary wireless
environment than the well-known uh like
you know actor critic or deep network or
like policy gradient network is much
more efficient than the average and
because there some of them is gets
sometimes the plateau and goes up and
it's it's classical behaviors of
reinforcement learning and then the uh
the loss function was more efficiently
stable in our scenario. And here I'm
finalizing my talk. Thanks for listening
for us. Now I think we can get some
questions.
Thank you.
Awesome. Okay.
>> Yeah. Martin, comments from any of the
other authors while I get everything
back going.
Yeah, we just were discussing among us
while you were gone. I think our talk is
kind of overwhelming nicely put or uh
more I know it's to some and it might be
even frightening you know not because
the topic itself you know but it's just
the ground we are covering you know we
go from Charles Darvin from Nicola Tesla
G application so it's just I think it's
well nicely put there are many many
things you could could ask question
about on the other hand you know you
might say so what is the major the the
one takeaway you know you know so so
Danny I feel for you you know I feel
sorry you know
>> yes I do have a few I guess entry points
um
>> especially for the the active inference
people who will be familiar with some of
the ways that the palm dps have been
presented so I guess just to begin with
in in the cyber fungal network? What
cognitive functions does it perform
and what kinds of transfer would you
expect or how do you adapt it to other
kinds of functionalities
like the kinds of things that that we
can use language models or other methods
for today?
So I would I would you know it's really
you have to understand it's like a real
brain you know so you have the different
cognitive functions such as perception
memory it's also a goal directed
behavior you know so these fungal
networks pursue a certain goal you know
it's kind of to build a an ecosystem a
community for exchanging not only
information but also tangible nutrients
you resources. So it's really it's
everything active inference
framework is in incorporating such as
goal directed behavior, memory, action,
perception
is found in the in in the uh root brain.
The interesting part for us is more kind
of okay we we don't want to build a
little AI or a little human brain. This
fungal networks happens to be the
largest living organism on planet earth.
So our goal was to build uh a 6G world
brain. So our motivation is then let's
learn from the largest living organisms
on planet earth which happened to be
this fungal network. And we are not at
the end of our question. So it's
something it's so it's promising
where to go next. I think it's it's
really this what what is currently
missing in 6G research this uh AI
embodiment and agentic AI. So these
fungal networks are underground in
nature but you might remember I also
said there are mushrooms. So mushrooms
are the fruing bodies of fungi. So put
differently the mushrooms help fungi to
embody the space above ground. So
mushrooms are like embodied fungi. So
this is one type of so mimicking fungi
for us
gives some ideas how to realize AI
embodiment and these mushrooms also
engage in certain activities. So
mimicking again mushrooms might give
some some hints uh at realizing aentic
AI. So this is from my side I I have to
say for now.
So the pom dp was able to select
different edges
and modify the network state. So the
memory is encoded in the network
topology and dynamics
and what what um about the token
encoding because you talked about the
token efficacy
of generative AI and active inference.
So I was wondering whether those were
observations
or whether the tokens were embedded
like they had already been passed
through an embedding model of a LLM.
So I hand it over to NA to give her the
opportunity to and
>> thank you. So uh here when we do when we
do this with DDPM okay it's like uh some
tokens when we have the so this is at
each step okay for 4,000 diffusion step
we are creating every DDPM graph
structure so we have 64 humans as this
connect together we have a link or not
if they have a link okay if there is a
link between two humans
there is a token as a reward assigned to
either of the humans. So one token to
one human at the end of one link and one
token to another human at the end of the
other link. This happens the same
exactly with the active inference. So
here we can say actually the network
that active inference creates has much
more less edges than the network that
DDPM creates. This is the meaning of
token assignment. So it has much less
edges
but it has the the same efficiency. Why?
Because the time it takes for social
contagion of all norms is the same
basically. And even for spreading
probability which equals to one or 100%
it means that um when some human has the
social norm the other one that has a
link to it 100% adopts the norm. So it
means that with uh in this condition
which r equals to one af time for social
contagion of all nodes is even uh less
than ddpm time. How how much less AI af
takes one time unit and DDPM takes 2.5
time units. Yeah.
>> Okay. So, the tokens are being they're
kind of a it's like a currency within
the simulation that's being passed
amongst the agents.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> So, and you're calling the nodes humans
and were they people or just a simulated
agent?
No, there are agents active inference
agents in active inference and um nodes
in DDP.
>> Okay. What was the teological
token?
>> Teological token is kind of a
reward-based token. Okay. It's a
purpose-driven token. So what is
[clears throat] our purpose here is to
uh as fast as we can we have to do the
social contagion of all nodes. So all of
the nodes in the network which is 64
humans have to adopt the norm. So we
want to see how fast and how efficient
is that and a token is like a cost for
us. Okay. Why this is a cost? because
we cannot have like as many as edges
that we want. Okay. But with so much uh
less edges, we can have the same level
of efficiency in active inference. So
like this is much better.
>> Okay. So h how do you go from what that
network does to the kinds of tasks that
people are working on or the kinds of
ways that people would want memory or
perception and action to be working.
>> Okay. So uh for for example perception
and action we had agent model
components. So we have some hidden state
factors for active inference. And these
hidden state factors then we have
agency. So we have actions. So because
active inference have to have a action
perception loop. Yeah. So uh they have
to act in the word. So what does cyber
fungi do? It actually assigns tokens to
each of them. So as I said it uh assigns
tokens to each of the humans that has
are at the end of the edges. So when
there is a edge we have two tokens for
each human. So cyber fungi does this and
also does the reviring. So for example
cyber fungi can remove one edge and add
one another edge. How does uh the cyber
fungi do this based on free energy
principle. So there are candidates. For
example, we want to add three edges.
Okay, there are candidates. And then
cyber fungi calculates the free energy.
What happens if we add this edge? What
happens to the free energy of the
network? And it only if it um reduces
the free energy, we can add that edge.
If not, we don't add that edge. So the
policy is uh move leading us toward uh
reducing free energy which is the based
on free energy principle by caron. Yeah.
>> So how would it memorize or operate on
like a text string? Right now there's
one kind of token being passed around
these different agents and then these
network topological
model selection driven operations.
So would it stay with one kind of
um
I'll let Martin back in. Would you
expect it to stay with one kind of token
or would there be multiple kinds of
tokens
to support
memory?
Uh with active inference we actually
don't have memory because uh like this
is randomly some candidates of edges are
uh selected then we have the free
energy. So we have to calculate the free
energy and go whether this reduces the
free energy over 4,000 steps. So because
we have 4,000 steps it is done like as
we want but with DDPM we have something
like a memory because it it has the
training data set. So it trains on 1.3
million networks small a small word
scale free networks and at the end it's
uh trying to create the same features
the small word feature and the scale
free features it creates it but like
with much more token cost
uh and also what was the other part of
the question sorry
>> whether you would sort of scale or
develop this with one kind of internal
network currency or multiple different
types.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We we can implement we can
definitely implement different kind of
tokens each of them meaning something.
For example, we define tokens as whether
there is a edge between two humans and
we assign two tokens to each of them.
But we can uh because this is a
purpose-driven token, we can assign
different tokens. So this this is based
on us like we can extend and our work in
this direction. Definitely. Yeah.
And is that um just remind what paper
and is that code available for that
first part?
>> Um the data set is available online but
I haven't uploaded the code yet and we
uh only submitted the paper and we are
waiting for the result but I will upload
the code soon.
>> Cool. Um yeah,
what what are the next moves? Like it
there's definitely a lot of sides to the
development of of your research, but
what do you feel like your next moves
are?
>> Yeah. Uh because we uh we did some kind
of embodiment here. So we did embodiment
with DDPM because [clears throat] of
some action that we did on it. But we we
want to push this burden. We want to
move forward with this embodiment. So as
we said, we are trying to move from the
fungal networks that are underground to
mushrooms. Now we want to get to the
above word. So mushrooms are the fruing
bodies or embodiment of the fungal
networks. So we want to move to some
kind of 3D spatial internet which we
want to implement it with the
holographic content to helps us with the
uh for example any use case that we want
with the social contagion we can do it
or we want to like have a real time 3D
spatial internet we are currently
working on that.
Osman or Martin want to add any sort of
closing comments? No,
>> I I I want to I want to hint at uh to at
Osman. I think this explanability
because active inference is very very
suitable for enabling explanable AI.
Maybe Osman you can make some comments
on
>> of course of course Martin. Uh as as I
said I mean I give a bit sneak peek of
results. So what our I mean most of the
uh um the focus was be nature of this
posterior beliefs it's very important
it's very informative side of this the
uh the the theory of active inference as
well as this the free energy
minimization so in that sense we can get
so many informative results in the
scenario of non-stationary wireless data
domains like as well as as I said radio
access networks so that's at the moment
our this two extended work is one on the
conference and then the paper but uh
there are also still so because it's
very new in our domain I mean um we we
can get of course we check now as I said
the
uh the agents stationational awareness
but we can also check the action and the
minimization of the free energy
principle um and the the let's say
interpretability
then we can get it more information
about the the agents behavior which is
very informative in the sense of again
uh very critical networks or low latency
applications as again one of the low
latency applications as the nika said is
holographic communications or like let's
say 3D internet in this type of settings
when you want to use this type of AI
agents it will be the like uh the one of
the like need and constraint will be the
trustworthiness so this will be our
extended works towards different use
case one another side I want to
definitely want to explore is um the
smart healthcare or like let's let's say
like this type of applications because
they are very vital so you need to be
very uh reliable in this networks even
if you are implementing some AI
algorithms
>> yeah definitely there's a lot of lot of
work there with the explanability and
the potion and semantic information
transfer [clears throat]
in a way is like explanability like
>> distilling some world processes to their
causal basis
>> is the accounting just taking a higher
resolution video is more syntactic
information but it doesn't necessarily
convey any further explainability.
So when like you pointed out there's
that cognitive agent to agent transfer
just increasing the bandwidth alone
doesn't capture or necessarily correlate
with the semantics of the communication.
So definitely a big emerging theme.
And because there's going to be these
different agents of different
embodiment,
you don't necessarily have one you
template which is kind of the importance
of having a unified cognitive approach
whether the communication is to
I guess a kitenbased or digital fungus
as it were.
Yeah, also lately I want slow like I
didn't again like small addition about
this explanability side of story you
know also because of the our like
interpretation of the free energy we can
basically get again like if you want to
like make it more interpretable a free
energy minimization story in the like
let's call it the agents behavior we
also check in our the paper like this
the so-called like preference or
information gain So which is important
because then we can also like understand
what is the tendency of the agent that
wants to do in this sense of scenario.
So that was also the one of the our like
let's say experiments in the paper. So
I'm we call it exttrinsic and epistemic
sort of uh exploitation. So that's why I
mean I'm if the results are coming I'm
happy to share and maybe the I was
checking today to maybe coming to next
active inference workshop and then to be
uh in uh you know interact with the
community about this works. Thank you.
>> Cool. Yeah definitely I know many people
will be interested to see the paper and
the code when they arise. Um, any
closing comments that either of you
would like to make?
>> Uh, thank you Daniel for hosting this
meeting and thank you for your time and
attention and your questions. We really
appreciate this.
>> Thank you so much for your time, Daniel.
Nice to meet you again.
>> Yes. So, good luck. Happy travels and
looking forward to the next steps in the
research.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Bye.
>> Have a good day.